December 25th, 1945
一九四五年十二月二十五日
Tomoko, the sun has set
友子，太阳已经完全没入了海面
I can't see Taiwan now
我真的已经完全看不见台湾扁了
Are you still waiting for me there?
你还站在那里等我吗*
Fuck you!
我操你…
Fuck you, Taipei!
我操你奸的台北 !
We can’t pass through
哇，运不能过喔 !
Yes, we can
可以啦，刚刚好 !
No, we can’t. Too low
不行啦，太低了啦
Yes, we can. Really
可以…真的可以…
Let's give it a try
试试看嘛，真的可以 !
Try what?
什感试试看=
We'll get stuck. Try your ass!
卡住就卡住了，膛试试看
Are you getting in or what?
你要不要上来了
Tomoko, come on!
友子,好了没
Wait a minute...
再等一下…
Come on! We don’t have all day here
要拍了， 没时间了
Tomoko, out!
友子，走开 !
OK, sorry
好了….对不起…
Back off please
再退伍一点…
Got good light. Keep it close together
光复很好，大家再靠票一点
Tight together. Come on. Excellent!
非常好 !
Good. Keep it close. Thank you
靠近一点，谢谢 !
That way!
从那亡…
Now, come on! Keep it close now...
很好， 靠近一点，靠…
Hey! What do you think you're doing?
嘿， 你以为你在干嘛=
Come on! Jeez!
搞什感
Tomoko, we're trying to shoot here What do you think you're doing?
友子，我们在拍照你在干嘛Y
All right, ladies. Never mind
好了 ， 各位不管了
Let’s do it professionally, all right? l want everybody in and smiling
专业一点，我想看到每个人的笑容
Good!
…非常好 !
Old Mao...
成伯 !
Registered mail!
持忠
Come on!
拜旗一下啦 !
A healthy young man has to work
年轻人好脚好手汽工作很翡嘉呢 !
Don’t force me, please
不是啦主席， 你不要涡我嘛 !
There’s no vacancy
就真的洛有缺啊 !
How could it be?
人怎友会没缺
Old Mao is 80 and he refuses to retire
像茂伯，要八十岁了还不退休
He doesn’t see you waving hands nor hear you calling him
跟他招手没看到， 叫他也汽黄到
He can’t be a mailman anymore
像那种人去途信不会有危险
You can’t go swimming
你们不行去游泳 !
You have work tomorrow and later on
你们明天跟等会儿都还有工作
What if you got sunburn?
如果不小心电黑了…该怎奉”
What we want is a dip in the water
只不过是玩玩水嘛 !
What are you hollering at?
整天大呼小叫的干什么
Don't be a bitch!
别像个老太婆一柑
Stop looking at the girls! Watch the road!
嘿，专心看路，不要只看女孩子 !
Hey! I'm also a model!
我也是个模特儿
How can you do it to me?
你们怎可以过样对我，靠 !
Watch out!
小心!
What the hell are you doing?
你们在干嘛=
I told them they'd get sunburn
我就说太阳那友大会电黑
They wouldn't listen. What can I do?
他们就是不了，我有什么办法
You don’t care about anything
你什么都府没天傈
But you want me to be responsible
然后又什么都要我负责
What do you want me to do?
你过样到底要我怎友做?
Hey, you!
喂!
You smoked in my bathroom?
你在我的遍所抽粳=
Don’t you think I'll tell the manager?
你不怕我跟你们烃理误哮*
Just paint it. Don’t waste your time
漆喷一喷就好了还贴，过友费工
Come on. It's done
来,好了…
Grandpa, he’s here!
阿公1来了!
First day at work and you're late
第一天上班就各厂晚到
You too
你不是一柑
You're late for school
汉点了还不上学*
From Hengchun Professional School...
和从师春工商那亡先跑
...to Junior High through Hengnan R. and to Elementary School through Beiman R....
走居南路到国中，北门路到国小
...to Zhongzheng R. and then Hsinhsing R.
走中正路接新绩路
This is the returned mail Give it back tomorrow
过个要退回的，明天回去交给杠栖
Any question?
有什么不清楚唉?
That's it. Go!
就过样啦，快去吧 !
You're late already
不然要泛到半夜了
Hey! You forget this!
喂， 过包你没拿
Fuck! You're dead!
干 ! 称死的 :
Jerk! So late on the first day!
死钦患子，第一天就晚一个多小时
Damn! Got me out and left me here
哭么 ! 把我扶出来，给我丢在运壬
Where are you from?
哪壬来的=
Post office’s motorcycle broke down
邮局的摩托车撞坏了在修理啦 !
Fuck! I thought you were mute
他妈的，我还以竹你哑巴
Why aren’t you wearing the helmet?
竹什么不戴安全帽=
Driver's license, please
砚照行照拿出来
What about him?
那个呢 =
And them?
那个
And her?
还有过个 !
And she ran through a red light too!
还关和红燃 !
There are plenty of them. Why me?
那友多人汉戴，为什么抓我一个
Because you're in a bad luck
因为你看起来比较倒岂
Driver's license!
思照 !
Don’t have it?
没带鹿照是不是Y
And driving without license too
再多开一休扰照右禹
What's your name?
叫什感名字?
What the fuck is your name?
我操他媚的你叫什感名字=
Shameless!
不要脉 !
Fuck!
堤!
I'll kill you!
我打死你 !
What the hell are you doing?
你干什么 ?
What are you doing?
你在干什么 !
Rauma, stop it!
汐马，你和给我住手 !
ll kill this motherfucker!
让我好好修理他
You're not in SWAT team anymore!
你以为你还是霹震小组喔 !
Come here!
你给我过来 !
Sorry...
对不起…
You! Maintain the traffic!
你，你去指挥交通…
Goddamn it!
他怒的!
What the fuck?
什感啊=
I'm sorry
对不起…
He’s in a bad mood
他最近心情不好…
Are you all right?
你有没有怎样
Why don’t you listen to me?
讲不匡耶你啊…
Come on!
不要运样啦 !
Come on! Don’t be a fool!
不要…不要过样啦 !
What's wrong?
人怎样
Can't start it!
发不动啦 !
It's tricky
你过很将搞喔 !
Why is it wrapped like this?
人怎友贴成吉样?
Wow! It’s convertible!
还做筹的
Do you have our mails?
有我们的信吧=
No!
没有啦 !
Can you fix it or not?
是能不能修理
All my tools are in there
工具都在里面
Then go get it!
那你去拿呀 !
My owner has the keys
欠匙在老头那这
You arrived just now?
你出回来的唉=
When'll your owner be here?
你老头是什么时候来啊?
He lives in there!
他就住在里面啊 !
Then why don’t you ring the bell?
是不会按电位喔 !
Amitabha, please...
阿引陀佛，各位车节…
Amitabha. I’m not Police
阿引陀佛，我不是土虱
I'm Frog, and I have no money
我叫做水蛙，我没钱 !
l replace you?
什么我接你的!
I've been in politics longer than you
玩政治我是比你有还久呢 :
I don’t replace you
我接你的
I let you be the mayor first
本来运镇长是我湾你先做的…
Mayor, excuse me. This needs your stamp now
镇长抱舟，吉份人家起著要萃章
Put it on my desk
你先放到我的桌上
All right. Put it there
放著就好…
Stamps? Everything needs my stamp
鞭章…哪有那友多章要莱*
Japanese singer's concert at the beach
日本歌手海潍演唱会
It's Mayor's most important job You have to learn how to do it
你如果要做镇长就要先学鞭章
Mayor, if you approve this...
镇发，过个你如果攻下去
..all the representatives will kill you
我们整个代表会是不会放过你喔 !
Tomoko...
友子
Please forgive my cowardice
请原访我去个丑弱的男人
I dared not admit we were in love
从来不到承认我们璀人的相爱
l even forgot how I became obsessed...
我甚至已经忘记
..with that rebellious girl...
我是如何迷上那个不照规定理及
...who upset me all the time
而惹得我大发雷霆的女孩了
Tomoko...
友子
You were stubborn and vain
你固执不讲理、爱玩爱流行
But I couldn't help being crazy for you
我全如此受不住的迷儿你
You graduated from the school...
只是好不容易你军业了
...when we lost the war
我们印战败了
We're losers
我是战败国的子民
Our aristocratism is no more
焉族的双傲瞬间齐落为犯人的柳
I'm nothing but a poor teacher
我只是个密教师
Why should I be the scapegoat?
移何要捕负一个民族的罪
l have nothing to do with the war
时代的宿命是时代的罪坎
I'm but a poor teacher
我只是个密教师
I love you, but I have to leave you
我爱你，条必须放秦你
O, Lord, let us praise together...
天父上帝阮再葛…
...and call thy name
议美称呼你尊名
Everybody, let's pray together
诸位兄姐，二时我们同心低头来福告
Malasun!
马拉桑 !
Miss, how are you?
小姐小姐，你好你好
l have an appointment with Mr. Huang
我跟你们黄主任有狗
Can you tell him I’m here?
可不可以攻我联绝一下
Wait a second, please
你稍等
Hello? Is Mr. Huang available now?
喂，请接一下黄主任
Miss, it's a new brand
小姐，过是一个全新的品牌
We repackage the aborigine’s millet wine
把原住民的小米酒重新包装
The goal is to go international
我们淮人备打入国际市场
Thousands years of history with new sensation
干年传统，全新感受
We named it Malasun
过酒叫马拉桑
I'll pour one for you
我先倒一杯给你喝喝看
No, thanks...
不要不要…
Yes? I have a Mr...
喂，主任，吉有一位…
...Mr. Malasun, who says he has an appointment with you
马拉桑先生褒跟你有狗
OK. The B1 office
好…B1闪公室
B1 office. No problem
BL，好好好…
The elevator is there
你从那伺坐电梯下去就可以了
Where's the general manager?
你们煽经理呢 =
Mr. Representative, can I help you?
代表…什么事情啊=
Have a seat, Mr. Representative!
那伺坐一下嘛 ! 代表 !
What is love?
情是什感玩意
It's nothing but a game
只不过是玩玩而已
Honey, darling, baby or pumpkin
Honey、dar1ing、bpaby
Whatever you call me
或是叫我小亲厅
Which floor?
你要到炮楼=
The basement
地下室 !
Can't you walk?
年轻人不会走楼梯啊 !
Don’t you have legs?
你没脚唉?
Sth floor!
五楼 !
Oh, I’m scared of nothing because I love you
喔，爱你爱到不怕死
But if you love someone else lI kill you for sure
但你若壁腿，就去死一死
Oh, I’m scared of nothing because I love you, baby
喔…爱你爱到不怕死baby
Please indulge me to show your love
爱我请你沾我癫狂一次
Who says Hengchun has no talent?
谁说咱们怖春泊人才
The church is done?
礼拜结束了吗”
Not yet
还没啊 !
Then why are you here?
那你怎磋在各?
Lord kicked me out of there
上帝把我超出来的
Mr. Representative, why so mad?
代表， 什么事情气成吉样
The hotel is yours, but the sea is ours
巴店你的，海我们管的啦 !
You think rich people can make everything BOT?
以为有铸就什么都8B0T
What are you talking about?
别运床说啦， 什么你们的、我们的
We have to go global now
现在时代在进步，要有国际届念
It's a global village
要有地球村的观念
What global village?
什么地球村=
You outsiders build up hotels here
你们外地人来各壬开骤店、做经理
The lands BOT. The mountains BOT
土地要B0T，山也BOT
Now the sea BOT too
过海也要和给我BO0T
What about us natives? Be employed?
我们在地人呢 * 都出外当人家网计
-Are we living on the same Earth? -Hey!
过像住同一颗地球上唉? -喂…
Where are you going?
代表你要去哪Y
Here it is!
过问啦 !
Open the door then!
不会开门喔 !
Why can’t people see it?
我们自己部看不到
Why?
过是为什么
Because rich people bought it too
因为有铸人违海都买去了
They left us nothing
邹不留一点和给我们
The annual Spring Scream is in Hengchun
每年我们怖春都在春天响喊
What about us natives?
我们在地人呢=
What do we get?
有什和三享受=
We can only cheer with the crowds
有啦 ! 在台下跟著咳咳叫
And all we get is garbage everywhere
最大的福利，就是捧二圾
Come on! We have nothing to do with Spring Scream
拜旗，春天呐喊跟我们又没关傈
This year we invite...
过回我们从日本请来的
...a famous singer from Japan
是真正出名的那个叫什感…
What's his name again?
疗伤歌手啦 !
His voice is like the sea...
那歌蓝像大海…
I don’t care if your Japanese singer...
我不管你请来的日本歌星
..iS going to be a doctor or a sailor
是要当医生还是要当船遇
What I’m asking you...
我跟你要的
...iS to have a local warm-up band
是暖场的乐围要找我们在地人
Do you understand me?
你是册不懂喔”
But there’s no local band here
可是你们在地就没乐围啊 !
I want gaiety this time
我过一场，要和给他办的很热病
That's why we need killing bands
所以我们要请很热半的乐转
You have no such talents here
你们和运就泊有过样的人才
What are you talking about?
你现在在说什么 ?
You? We?
还分你们、我们Y
What happened to your global village?
你刚克不是襄不要分
What do you mean?
什感意思啊=
I mean...
我是说…
All right, whatever
好啦…不管怎样
l assure you that I can get...
我就是可以从在地过里
...a great local band for you
找出一个加水淮的乐围给你
No. it’s impossible
不可能啦 !
Yes, it’s possible
有可能啦 !
Believe me when I say it’s possible
跟你说有可能就有可能啦 !
Or let's run for the Mayor next year
要不然我们明年一起来选镇长
Wait and see who will be elected
看谁导的上=
Come on! Please!
拜旋，你别运样嘛 !
I promised those people in Taipei
台北那亡我跟人家都已经谈好了
Why don’t you cancel it?
艾掉不就好了 !
We've paid them. How could it be cancelled?
钱都付了，要怎友给人家斜掉=
-Yeah! — -Listen, it’s all right
是啊 ! -我跟你说，没天傈 !
If you don’t want a local band...
假使速个表演乐围都不留给在地人
...[ won't let you party at beach...
就算是要几架镇长、绑架县长
..even if l have to kidnap the Mayor
我也不会沾你过个活动在海记表演
Let’s go!
我们走啦
Listen to me, please
主席, 你训我拜旗一下好不好=
Do you know how much money I’ve spent?
我吉次花了多少镀你知道吗”
l even get lots of foreign models...
我还请了很多外国的模特儿
.. for people to take photos with
来给人照相宣传
It's Integrated Marketing, you know?
过叫做整体行销，你知道吗”
I'm running for the Mayor next year
我跟你说，我决定明年要选镇长
Think about it. I'll give you 1 minute
你考虑看看，一分钾 !
Have you heard of Kousuke Atari?
主席, 你颈过中孝介吗”
Don’t you understand what I’m saying?
人话你英不懂耶 !
Wait...Wait a minute!
等等…慢点 !
All right!
好啦 !
I'll have your band
用你们的围啦…
No...our band
咱们的围啦…
Try it...
试试看…
What do you think? Is your mouth...
人怎友样 * 有没有感党酒香在螨里…
Wow! You really can drink
哇 ! 好酒量…女中豪保
Let me get you one more
我再倒一杯给你
Why?
入什感=
OK. I'll be right there...
好 我马上去…
What? They’ re leaving!
啊 要走了耶 !
OK. I'll be right there!
好 我局上 !
What the hell?
干什么?
I'm a model too
我也是模特儿
Why can’t I go on the runway?
竹什么你都不找我走秀
Why do you always ask me to be a caretaker and an interpreter?
老是要我做保姆做翻泽呢=
You're good looking
好，我知道…
But the current fashion doesn’t suit you
只是现在时尚的潮流就是不适合
You look good actually
其实你的型很KK
You're still young, you know?
你还年轻好不好 !
I'm old!
我老了 !
I'm so upset that I age early
我已经被你气老了
I stay here in Taiwan after graduation
我学校蛙业后还原意留在台洪
because you said that 1 was special
就是因为你跟我府我很有特色
Now you say I’m not in trend...
现在你反而褒我不流行
..and that l can only be an interpreter?
只能当个翻渤*
Please, don’t start with me
大小姐你就惠帮忙好不好
It's an emergency. We had no choice
过个案子很突然
But it’s a lifetime chance
但机会公是很允得呀 !
The Japanese label doesn’t believe...
日本的唱片公司他们不相信
.. they can get proper musicians...
他们可以在恒春那个地方
..in such a place like Hengchun
找到适合的乐手
Do me a favor, please
所以我拜旗你
Supervise everything there
你就先在那亡监督一下
Be a caretaker
挺一下，看一下 -不管怎样
Anyway, you can’t ask me to stay without asking for my consent
你不可以问都汽问，就把我留下来
You can’t do that
不可以过样子的
The key to Miss Tomoko’s room
友子小姐的房卡
You know the Japanese are so picky
你也知道日本人做事就是最钨毛
We don’t know how to deal with them
也最准搞的啊 !
When you speak ill of the Japanese...
你要讲日本人坏话时
... don’t forget I'm Japanese too
请你记得我也是个日本人好吧”
Why should we cancel our plans?
说好的党围干嘛鬼来沟去 !
You're late every day. Lazybones!
你每天七晚八晚，散散漫漫的
What do you think you're doing?
是在干什么=
I don’t work here
我又不是在各壬上班 !
Schedule your route today
今天路笋你自己排
I'll see if it's appropriate
排好我再看行不行
The 3rd day
第三天
How could I stop myself from thinking about you?
该怎友克制自己不去想你
You're a student from the sunny South
你是南方况阳下成长的学生
while I’m a teacher from the snowy North
我是从标雪的北方渡洋明海的老师
We're so different
我们是过友的不同
But why do we love each other so much?
移何分会如此的相爱
I miss the sunshine and the warm winds
我侠念周阳…我司念热风…
l remember you were upset by the ants
我狼有记居你被红虹惹毛的样子
I know I shouldn't laugh at you
我知道我不该嘲笑你
But the way you stamped on the ants... It fascinated me
但你踩著红虹的样子真美
It's as if you were dancing...
像踩著一种奇幻的舞步
.. with anger and airing joyfulness
愤奶、强烈又带著轻挑的嫩笑…
That was when I fell in love with you
友子，我就是那时爱上你的…
Attention, everyone
咱城南里各位里民请注意收匠…
We have an audition at 7:30 this evening
今天晚上七点半在镇公所活动中心
All those who can play any instrument are welcome to attend
有一声乐器表演的挑愤活动
Your ID card, please
身分证呢?
My ID card is needed?
还要身分咀
Don’t you have it? Then how do I know if you're native
没身分渤我哪知道你是外地还在地的
Move! Don’t you see I’m limping?
关啦 ! 没看到跋脚喔=
Get out of my way!
闪…上内啦 1
This kid is impossible. Move!
过小孩都说不央，内一这去啦 !
Hsiang, eat it by yourself
翔翔你要自己吃喔 !
Number 107? All right...
十号，好啊…
You're the best. Eat it by yourself
翔翔最稍，自己吃喔 !
Ma’am, my friend registered for me...
老关娘，我朋友刚刚攻我报名
...to play the drums in an audition
要到活动中心表演打鼓
Okay, you're free to go
好啊，要去你就去啊 !
Do you want to see me performing?
你要不要来看我表演=
Who would take care of these kids?
我去* 过三个小孩子谁照顾
Take them with you then
活动中心小孩子可以进去啊 !
-Do you want to go? = -Yes!
要去唉? -好 !
Hey, you! Stop!
你，别跑…
Stop...
别跑啊…
Ask your people to be quiet, please
请你的镇民们安静点好唉”
Stop the racket!
不要吵 !
Quiet!
安静啦 !
Quiet! Do you hear me?
安静没丹到
Where are those 3 kids from?
那三个青子是谁的?
Get them out of here!
带出去啦 !
Let me tell you something...
防尾，阿公跟你讲…
Be quiet when someone's performing
人家在表演，还过样大小普
Otherwise it'd seem so rude
没礼角 !
Old Mao!
茂伯啊 !
Finished already?
人怎友过快就完了=
Finished?
结束了唉=
Applaud!
鼓掌啊 !
Number 10, it’s your turn
十号，损你表演了
Number 10? Shit! It’s me!
十号* 哭爸，是我啦 !
Number 10...
十号…十号. .
Take care of these kids for me please
香肠的，和拜雹，絮我顾一下 !
Number 10!
十号 !
What are you doing?
你干嘛=
Number 10! It's me!
十号…十号啦 !
Who’s spraying water?
搞什感水优喷 !
That's not water. It's saliva
过不是水，是口水
You're disgusting!
你很航侠耶 !
I didn’t think you would come
我还以为你不来了
Take it
拿去
Or I will crash it
不然我摔精它
How dare you?
你摔看看
Well, go ahead and do it
有脆子你摔看看
See that?
看到汽有、
There goes Hengchun’s drum player
我们臣春的鼓开工了啦 !
Are you going on stage?
你有报名唉”
It won't hit you...
不会中…
See? I told you. What are you afraid of?
就跟你说不会中你怕什感
Hey, Mr. Postman
喂，途信的
Playing guitars is supposed to make you happy
弹吉他是一件很快乐的事
Old Mao, please!
茂伯， 不要来优啦 !
Put it away!
收起来啦…
My wife and your father died early
我老婆和你老爸都很早就死了
My kids are working elsewhere
我杷个表子都出外在工作
Your brothers are away either
你汉个兄弟也都出门在外
Only your mother and I are left here
只剩我和你媚一个人
We're so lonely
很孤单呢 !
The house is big...
房子是那友大问
..and the bed is large...
床又那友大项
Come on!
拜旗好不好
Speaking about the house makes angry Why should you mention the bed too?
讲到房子就已经火大了“，还讲到床
The priest says...
人家教会牧师也说了
.. that it's not good to be alone
一个人不好 !
That was why their God created women
他们的上帝才会又创造了女人
People are meant to be social
人本来就是要相互在一起嘛 !
l hope you understand
希望你能体谅 !
He’s the only one who can play drums
只有过个人会打鼓
You can’t ask him to because of that
不能因为只有一个会打鼓就叫了他打
You don’t think he’s good enough?
他打的不好是不是
That's not the point
表演不是好不好的问题
What matters is how he charms the audience on stage
而是舞台魅力
He looks like an insect
他长得跟昆焉一样
What insect?
什么昆副*
You look down upon him already
都还没开始，水蛙看成蟾内
Frog!
水蛙
The rehearsal is 7:30 at the Hotel basement
今天晚上七点半骤店地下室精打鼓
I picked you among others
干挑万寻才滤到你的
Don’t let me down
不要和给我漏气
Remember, put your feelings into it
记得，放感情去打知不知道
Come on!
加油啊 !
This aborigine is good at mouth organ
吉原住民吹口琴不错啊 !
Mouth organs are not for a rock band
挥滚乐围吹口琴谁匠得见啊?
Says who? He played drums yesterday...
谁说的，人家昨天又打鼓
..and guitar and mouth organ. It was great
又弹吉他又吹口琴 , 很好颈耶 !
Everyone loved it
那个每个人都…哇，拍拍手 !
Ask him to play the bass guitar then
不然就叫吉个弹具斯啊 !
What does a mouth organ player know about the bass guitar?
吹口琴的怎友会弹具斯 *
Goddamn it!
哭天!
Those DoReMis are the same anyway
弹具斯和吹口琴不是一柑DoReM]i
I bet he knows how to play them both
会吹那个就会弹那个啦 !
You think I know nothing about music?
你以为我不懂香乐喔=
What the hell are you doing?
你是来筷的是不是
You play the bass guitar Your son plays the guitar
你负责弹具斯，你儿子弹吉他
I don’t know how to play bass guitar
我不会弹有具斯啊
It's OK. Everything will be fine
没关傈啦，去了就会了
All right, that’s it then
好啦， 反正就吉样决定了啦 !
And the lead vocal...
那主唱…
Go get Mr. Representative’s...that kid!
主唱就叫代表主席…他那个啦 !
Wait a minute...Who’s that?
等一下…那个，那个是谁Y
Was he there yesterday?
昨天有来吗?
The one who got mad playing the guitar
就咱天弹吉他弹到翻腑那个啦 !
Can he sing?
那个会唱歌咀*
Don’t look down upon him
你真的很看不起人慎
He was a lead vocal in a Taipei band
人家之前在台北乐团也是主唱耶
He can write, play and sing
会寅， 会弹，又会唱
How often do you meet a talent like him?
吉人才你是去哪壬找啊=
What are you complaining about?
你是来筷的是不是=
Did I say anything?
我有说话唉”
This is men’s talk
你没看到男人在那里讨论
What are you moaning about?
你女生在那亡喷喷喷…
Your tooth aches? Why don’t you see a doctor?
你耻效痛 * 牙交痛不会看医生喔
Ignore her. Come on...
不用管她啦，来…和继稿…
The one who plays keyboard is too old
过弹键盘的太老了…都欧巴桑 了
Old? How about this one? She’s 40
太老 * 不然就各个，过个40蕨
Look how beautiful our sea is
你看我们的海运厂漂亮
Why can’t young people stay here?
入什么一些年轻人就是留不住
Tomoko, take a look at our sea...
友子，你看我们的海…
I don’t understand your dialect!
我双不懂台语 !
7 o'clock tonight at Chateau Hotel
妹妹，晚上七点夏都酒店
You'll join the band on our behalf
你代表我们师春参加乐团
What about my grandpa? Is he in?
我阿公呢 Y* 我阿公有被玩到唉=
Come on! It’s a rock band
拜苞，我们过是摇滚乐
Old Mao can only play yukin
你们茂伯是弹月琴的
Son of a bitch!
死钦患子 !
Malasun!
马拉桑 !
What did you say?
马…马上什么啦
It's Malasun
不是马上“，是马拉桑
Damn! It's 7:30 now
哭天，现在七点半了
Till 9 o'clock? What's wrong with you?
弹到九点，要弹给史册Y
Enough! I want to talk to your manager
别褒那友多，叫你们经理来跟我讲
Frog!
水蛙
-Have your feelings with you? -Yeah...
有没有带感情出来 -有…
Put your feelings into it, all right?
用感情下去打，知道吗”
You're in it too?
你们也都有喔
I'm Frog
水蛙啦水蛙 !
The drummer
鼓手鼓手啦 !
Frog!
水蛙啦 !
-How are you? = -Frog!
你好… -水蛙!
When were you back?
你什么时候回来的=
My daughter
我女儿
She's so cute
好可爱喃 !
Leave her alone
你别惹她…
I'm the drummer, your mom’s friend
我鼓手，你媚的老同学
How do you do? I’m Frog the drummer
你好， 我是鼓手水蛙
Insect! Go back where you came from
你和过焦昆患，还不快答我现出原形
I'm sorry
对不起 日文)
Where's Aga?
我们阿嘉呢?
God knows!
去问神啊 !
Forget it. Let’s start the rehearsal
好了 不用等了，你们自己精 !
Rehearse what? It’s our first day
要和练什感 * 今天第一天呢 !
Yeah, we don’t have the score and we don’t know each other
是啊，也没有谱，大家也都不熟
Hi, I'm Hong Kuo-rong
你好， 我叫洪国业
The town council chairman
我就是代表会主席
Hi, I'm Frog the drummer
你好，我鼓手，我叫水蛙
I know! I picked you personally!
我知道啦 ! 你是我愤的啦 !
I'm the town council chairman I'm 170 centimeters tall
我是代表会主席,身高170
l weigh 75 kilograms and I’m 60 years old
体重75，今年60诚
What I love most to do is...
我最大的归超
... quarrel, fight, kill people and set a fire
就是吵架、 打架、针人、放火
And my ambition...
而我最大的心愿
..is to burn down Hengchun...
就是把整个恒春放火烧掉
..and to ask all the young people...
然后把所有年轻人
...to come back here to rebuild it
叫回自己家乡，重新再造
We'll be the employers, not the employees
自己做老头，别出外当人家网计
Do we know each other now?
过样我们训悉了吗 =
Yes! It hurts!
有啦 ! 会痛啦 !
All right already! Calm down!
主席, 好了…别生气…
Yeah, calm down...
好了， 别生气啦…
You said something too!
你也有讲啊 !
What are they doing downstairs? Band?
楼下在干嘛=* 张围
Can you lower your voice?
以答可不可以请你讲话小坦一点
You scared me!
嘛死人啊你
Here!
拿去 !
Do you clean the cup before it's passed on to someone else?
一个酒杯各友多人喝，有没有洗=
Yeah
是的 :
They're rehearsing now
他们已经开始练习了
Il see
是过柑啊 !
I'll report to you in a couple of days
我过两天再将情形跟你报告好吗”
I've informed our Taipei Office
台北公司我已经府过了 !
Yeah
是的
Yeah, I see
是的，我知道了
What the hell are you doing?
你搞什感
Mind your tempo
忽快忽慢的
Stop fooling around!
来天的啊Y
Take your call outside!
讲电话出去好不好 !
You're getting nearer and nearer
你一天一天越气越靠过来
It's next to me today
今天乾脆直接气在村栖旁亡啊
I've had enough!
你过不过份啊你?
Malasun!
马拉桑 !
l have and appointment with your general manager...
我跟你们炉经理有狗…
Mr. Representative...
代表…
I'm Hakka in Baoli. Here’s my calling card
我保力那亡的客家人，名片在过
This is our new product
过是我们公司和信义乡农会
Revolutionary millet wine
合作的新产品小米酒
It's called Malasun
叫做马拉桑
Age-old tradition with new sensation
干年传统，全新感受
This is for you. Try it please
过瓶途你，试试看 !
He’s waiting for you upstairs
他已经在楼上等你了，请你上楼
Thank you
谢谢
Mr. Representative...
代表…
I'm the only salesman in Hengchun
现在整个恒春，只有我一个业务
I'm wondering if you can help me...
我想褒可不可以攻个忙
..and introduce me to other hotels
介绍我去别家骤店
My boss wants this new product...
因为过次我们的产品
...to be high-class
我们老关想要走高级路入
Please. Do me the favor
拜旗一下，拜旗…
Baoli belongs to Checheng
你保力是车城
This is Hengchun here
我过壬是恒春
Why should I help you?
我为什么要攻你Y
Have some pride, young man
少年人，有志气一点
Stop kissing someone's ass for money
不要一天到晚为了赚钱去捧人LP
Yeah, not bad
还好，还不错
I've been watching them rehearsing
目前每天都盯著他们在练习新歌
Yeah, the first song will be ready this week
是的，第一首歌会在过过和练好
The second one by this weekend
第二首歌也会在过末前做出来
The weather's gone mad and the sea is boiling
天和气瘤了，海水滚了
That's why I want to seize the day
所以我要扰乐不作
Stop wasting time
不要浪费每一刻，快乐
Be a skywalker...
当莫的天行者…
Stop...
停停…
What?
人怎样
I'm adding something here
过亡我还要加个东西
Be a skywalker...
当芝的天行者
All right, whatever. As you wish
好啦，随便啦，你们高旺就好了
One more time!
再来一个 !
-When the sky is empty... -Wait...
天是空的… -等一下…
After that...
关才那个结束之答
...l'll try something cool. Come on!
我再试一个更好玩的, 来 !
Hey!
喂!
Can you try it after we do it once?
能不能从厌到尾走过一忆再发表意见
It's been 3 days
到现在都已经三天了
We haven't finish anything yet
都还没从厌到尾走过一忆
You, with the keyboard!
你啦 ! 弹键胡的
Mind your tempo
速度忽快忽慢
The bass guitar is lagging
有具斯手永束跟不上和节拍
Drummer can’t stop criticizing
鼓手的意见又过友多
What the hell do you want?
到底想怎样 * 要不要和练啊?
What? Stop moaning!
是怎样啦 * 是怎样啦
You look down upon us, don’t you?
你瞧不起我们就对了
You're the best, all right?
你弹的最好就对了啦 !
Only you can say anything
每次都只能你有意见
What do you want?
不然你想怎磋柑?
What? Wanna fight?
人怎友样 * 你想摔是不是?
I'd like to point out 3 things
有三件事我想讲
First, the keyboardist is too young
第一，我沈得弹键盘的太小了
. while the bass guitarist is too old
弹有具斯的又太老了
We have to find someone else
我希望各两个人一定要再找过
Second, you're a mess
第二，我沈得你们现在真是一围秽
We should rehearse more often
一定要增加练习时间
Third!
第三!
They want you to write 2 songs
日本公司那伺希望我们有两首歌
But there’s only one now...
但是，到现在我只其到一首而已
.. written by you a long time ago
而且吉首歌还是你很久以前写的
But what matters is the other song
不过，重点是另外一首
Can you do it?
行不行啊?
Can you do it if l can’t?
不行你能解决唉?
I'm not in charge here
我又不是围长
Ride to hell!
撞死你 !
Aga...
阿嘉
When are you normally off duty?
你每天都途信泛到雹点?
Around 5 o'clock
差不多五点吧
5 o'clock?
五点喔 !
You're fast, aren't you?
你过个新来的手脚算快嘛 !
Put the mails inside the mailbox to avoid them being stolen
你信丢信箱丢深一点，别让人拿走
I've got complaints about losing mails
最近有人在反应信都收不到
Hey, girl!
喂，女孩子
Who do you want?
你要找谁吗=
Excuse me...Is Aga here?
对不起，请问阿嘉住在过亡吗=
He’s off to work. What do you want?
他去途信了 ! 你要找他做什么?
He won't be back until late afternoon
他可能下午才会回来喔
I'm the coordinator of the band
我是饭店乐围的联络人
This CD is for his reference
我有一张C0要让他当作曲的参考
Please give it to him
麻烦你攻我拿给他好唉=
So, you're that Japanese girl?
喔，你就是那个日本女孩子*
Come on. Come in, please
来…进来里面坐 ! 进来…
No, thanks. I'll write him a note
不用…我需张字人条给他就好了
Won't you come in and have a seat?
你真的不进来坐Y
You're Japanese...
你日本人需我们中文
I'm sorry. Are you all right?
抱租…有没有怎模*
I didn’t mean to hurt you
不小心催到油门的
My betel nut...
捧术构哩…
What is it?
你怎磋了…
I'm fine
我洛有怎友样…
Are you all right?
怎友样?
I can't see
我的眼睛看不见
Wipe them clean! I can’t see...
把它擦掉，和卫生狐啦 ! 我看不到…
Help him up
你来扶他一下
My legs are fine
我的脚洛有问题 !
Get on!
上车啦 !
Wipe them clean!
擦乾汉啦 !
Excuse me...well...
请问一下，那个…
Thank you
谢谢 !
What happened? Are his hands hurt?
人怎样啦 * 手有没有受伤?
Damn!
哭天!
What happened to your nose?
鼻子怎友贴成吉柑
He’s hurt already and you put an X on his nose?
就已经在豪了，膛和给他打叉 !
His wound is right here
他德在各壬…
l have to avoid his eyes and nose tip
贴横的中眼睛，贴直的中鼻椒
What else can do?
我哪有办法
What are you laughing at? He’s in pain
笑什么啦，人家在难过了还笑 !
You really know how to play this?
你过样叮叮噬噬，弹也弹不成铀
Can you do it?
过样也行咀Y
It's not what you're thinking!
那个不是啦 !
Aga!
阿嘉!
Please! Don’t tell anyone!
拜旗一下，你不要讲啦 !
He’s young and ignorant Why don’t you help him?
年轻人不懂事，你就玫忙途一下
Don’t I have anything better to do?
我吃鲍太闻
I'm old and limping and you want me to help him?
我坏者了又跋脚，还要攻你途”
How many times have I told you?
我再三的交代，你还运样筷搞
What if it’s notifying someone's...
如果人家和结婚、生子
.. wedding, giving birth or death?
或是出列的通知怎友办
We have phones. Who writes letters anymore?
现在都打电话了“，哪有人写信
Damn you!
哭天啊 !
Are you working for the post office or the phone company?
你是在邮局有还是在电信局啊?
Old Mao, don’t tell anyone please
茂伯，你不要说…
Come on. I don’t need money
别运样…我洛有缺钱 !
Buy whatever you like with it
看你喜积什么就去买嘛 !
I like playing music
我就爱弹琴啊 !
Buy a new instrument then
爱弹琴就去买新的琴嘛 !
Who am I playing for?
我弹琴要弹给谁贡=
Who wants to listen to...
现在什感时代了
...us old people playing?
还有人骏我们各些老的弹琴
The newspaper says I’m a gem
报和引都报说我是国需
Who gives a damn?
需个芋仔番薯啦 ! 谁在稀罕
If 'm a gem, I should go out and show them...
像我们过种国吉，就要出去让人欣赏
.. instead of staying at home
不是放在家里当神主牌
Only hundreds of them They won't give you so hard a time
就友百张信没途，礁该不会卡份太重
l heard someone got in jail for opening private letters
以前还册过和给和人家偷拆信和被判刑的
I told you it’s not that!
就跟你说过各不是啦 !
What is it then?
不然那是什感=
Porno?
黄色的=
How I wish a storm would come now...
多希望过时有暴风
...and drown me in the ocean between Taiwan and Japan
把我淹疙在过台湾与日本问的海域
Then I won't have to be responsible for my cowardice
过样我就不必往了我的惨弱负责
Tomoko...
友子
I've been sailing for several days
才泡天的航行
The weeps brought by the sea wind
海风所带来的哭葛
age me already
已泪我着者许多
I don’t want to leave the deck
我不愿享开甲板
or go to bed
也不愿睡觉
I've made up my mind
我心守已经做好租算
Once ! land...
一旦让我著陆
..I'll no longer see the ocean
我将一尼子不原再看见大海
Sea wind, why do you always bring the weeps?
海风啊，为何和是带来哭普呢
They weep for being in love, for marrying someone
爱人哭、嫁人器
or giving birth
生孩子器
l weep when I think of you marrying someone else
想著你未来可能的幸福我粮是会器
But the sea wind dries my tears...
只是我的汽水
...before they drop
篇是在潮出前就被海风吹乾
I can’t cry any tear, which ages me even more
渤不出汽水的哭泣，澡我更苔老了
Curse the wind!
可恶的风
Curse the moonlight!
可恶的月光
Curse the seal
可恶的海
I told you already!
我上次就跟你讲过
The bass guitarist was too old
弹具斯的那个欧吉桑太老了
Now you have someone even older
你今天又损来一个更老的 !
It was not me who asked him here
人又不是我找的，关我什么事=
I'm not in charge here
乐团又不是我负责
You're not in charge?
你不负责=
All right, I'll see how you're going to sing on stage
好 那到时我看你在全上怎唱 !
I love my girl
我爱我的妹妹呀 !
I love you so much
哥哥真爱你
When we were in the park...
那当时在公园壬
...do you know what happened?
怎厅了你可知
l saw the moonlight...
看见月色渐渐亮…
You really want him to use that as a bass guitar?
你真的让他拿那个当有目斯吗?
I bet that old man...
那个老头，我敢打赌
...never touched a bass guitar
他从出生到现在一定泊有拿过具斯
Our Japanese singer will be here soon
还有赤天日本歌手就要来了
What can we do now?
人怎且办=
What about your other song?
还 有你的第二首歌呢 =
l haven’t seen anything!
连个影子都还没有 !
Have you listened to the CD I gave you?
我给你的CD你了了唉=
Look at him!
你看，他过样 !
Don’t tell me writing songs is not your job
不要跟我说作曲不是你负责的 !
What are you doing?
干什和三啊?
Look!
你看 :!
It's salt!
距巴 !
He spent his time at the beach
他做不出曲子还有空去海短玩水
You've been late everyday
你每天召到
I thought you were busy writing songs
我都以为你在作曲才没有褒你
Now I know that you were at the beach
原来你跑到海亡玩水
How can you be so mean?
你们不要太过分 !
I quit!
我不干了 !
Get out of my way!
走开啦 !
Why didn’t you say anything?
你怎友都不讲话啦 !
Do you understand anything she said?
他讲哪一国中文你其得懂啊=
Wow! The Japanese eats everything!
喔,日本人什么都敢吃 !
l see the moonlight sprinkling
看见月色渐渐亮
l have something to tell you
有话对你讲
Please think about it, girl...
妹妹你呀想一想
What are you doing?
要干什么
How do you play this thing?
过哪记是头啊?
Hey! Are you leaving?
喂，你就过样走啦?
Hey! Japanese girl!
喂， 你过个日本人
Your job is not done. Why are you leaving?
答应的事怎友可以没做到就训开 !
Miss Tomoko, what's wrong with you?
友子小姐…你怎腰了=
Miss Tomoko!
友子小姐…
Miss Tomoko...
友子小姐
The grandson of my younger brother is getting married today
过是我弟弟的长生今天娶媳妃
We have the reception this evening
晚上在庙口有酒席
Please come and enjoy with us
请和我们一起同高是吧 !
We'll be waiting for you
今晚请一起来吧 !
Congratulations
恭喜
I'm the bass guitarist of the band
我是乐围弹具斯的
I want to practice a little
今天闻著想说来缚一下
Look, Mr. Representative!
主席, 你看 !
This Hakka is so diligent
各个客家人过亡拼
He works day in and day out
晚上顾邹店，白天跑店面
Diligence is the only strategy he knows
曹电找狗屎啦 !
The bottles of wine he’s sold today...
你看人家今天跑的外务
...are more than the mails at Aga’s
比他们阿嘉堆在家里的信膛多 !
Shit!
堤!
Nothing...
没事啦…
Hey! Malasun!
嘿 ! 马拉桑 !
Chateau Hotel. May I help you?
夏都你好， 是
60 bottles?
60泪
OK...Thank you. Bye
好好…谢谢…拜拜 !
Let me show you one more time
我再弹一次给你了…
Why can’t I do it right?
过柑也不对，和那样也不对
What can I do?
什么都不对 !
Malasun!
马拉桑 !
What the hell?
干什么啦 !
Let me show you. It’s...
我教你弹…
Malasun! You hit the jackpot!
马拉桑 ! 你做到大生意了 !
Mr. Representative called...
刚刚代表主席打电话来
...and asked for 60 bottles of wine
要你晚上淮备60瓶小米酒
For the wedding reception
到大庙会塌喜宴 !
I'm sorry...
不好意思…
60! 60 bottles...
60瓶啦…60撼…
Malasun, you know Mr. Representative well?
马拉桑…你跟代表主席很熟唉”
Please give this old man a chance
拜旗，和给老人家一个机会
Don’t tell him you can play, please
别说你会弹琴啦 ! 拜旋啦 !
Malasun! Hi, everyone!
马拉和桑 ! 大家好…
It's on Mr. Representative
代表主席请的
Our company’s new product Malasun millet wine
我公司的新产品马拉桑小米酒
Aga!
阿嘉!
Come on...Bon appetit!
来来…菜来了 !
Miss Tomoko...
友子小姐
This is Aga’s mother
过是阿嘉他媳媚
I've seen her. She visited us once
我有看过，他来过我们家
Sit there!
那亡先坐 !
Harder!
再用力一点 !
Next! Mr. Chen Kuang-hui
下一位，陈光辉先生请淮备
Here ] am! I’m Chen Kuang-hui
过庄…陈光粳我本人
Dad, my head aches! Stop!
爸爸，头很痛很计展
All right!
好了啦 !
I don’t need help!
不用扶啦 !
Idiot!
白痴
Wow! You really can drink!
酒量好是不是
Why are you dressed like this?
水蛙有还包装成吉样，辟张喔 !
I don’t know. Well...
我哪知道，我想说…
Sit there...
那这坐…
There’s no seat here
过按没位子了 !
I'll... sit there instead
不然我…坐那桌好了 !
Hi, Ma’am
老头娘
Why are you dressed like this?
你怎厂穿成吉柑?
Uncle Frog, you’re handsome!
水蛙叔坡，你真闻 !
Thank you, Mr. Lin
感潮林代表的歌普
You're so cute!
好可爱喔 !
Stop, you chicken! I'll get you!
给我记住，胆小鬼给我记住
Go on...Cheer for Daddy
去…去和给爸爸加油 !
Go on, cheer for Daddy
阿志，快去给爸爸加油
Now...“Whirling Neon Light”
现在来唱和吉首“转吧七彩需虹燃”
You have suits like this one?
你怎友会有过套?
The boss is drunk again
老头又喝醉了*
This is for you
老关娘，各途你
The December sea is filled with anger
十二月的海各是带著慎妈
I tolerate the shame and regrets...
我承受著也辱和悔恨的臭味
... accompanied by uneasiness
陪同不安静地网漫
Not sure I’m going home...
不明白我到底是如乡
...or leaving home
还是享郑 !
Hey, friend...
朋友
This is my princess
过是我的鲁凯公主
Isn't she pretty?
长得很漂亮喃
If you see her, please tell her...
如果你有看到她的时候
...that I no longer take risks
告诉她…我已经不再嘉命了
I'm back here for a peaceful life
我已经回来当一个安分的小警察
Please?
好不好=
Mr. Representative...
代表…
It's the last bottle. Cheers!
最答一瓶，我误你
No, I have more
不用啦， 过壬还有
Il do it
不然我自己来啦 !
I'll leave it here
我运瓶留在过里 !
Enjoy yourself. Thank you
慢慢喝， 谢谢
This Hakka is really...
各个客家人“，实在很…
It's all right. Pll go. You eat
没关傈，我去就好，你都还没吃
He always gets drunk and falls
时常吉样…想摔倒就摔倒
Mr. Representative!
主席啊
How are you? Long time no see
你好 ! 很久不见了
Fine. I’m great
好 ! 好啦…
This is my wife
过我老婆啦 !
Is she pretty?
漂亮吗?
Here. Propose a toast over there
过瓶拿著，去敬丛面那桌
They're waiting for you. Go ahead...
你都没去敬合面那桌，快去…
He was at the SWAT team in Taipei
以前在台北当迅雷小组
You know them, always taking risks
你也知道那种队遇，只有半休命啊 !
Sometimes they were gone all day long
有时候早上出门，晚上回不了家
His wife left him because of it
他老婆受不了，就过样享家出走
He’s always in a bad mood
心情坊啊 !
Once he fell from the 3rd floor while he was chasing the perpetrator
有次出勤务…
I want to sing
好想唱歌喔 !
He was hurt badly Stayed at the hospital for six months
伤到答椎骨， 在医院得了半年
Then he was reassign here, back home
没办法，出院后铀回家戎
-Tomoko? = -Get off me!
友子…” -不要碰我 !
-Tomoko!  -l said get off me!
友子”-叫你不要碰我 !
First love is filled with emotions
初邵爱情酸甘甜，五种气味喃
I flush when she says she loves me
那了一句我爱你，满腑就征咳咳
The girl is happy
尤其是小姑娘，心内是真区喜
But she pretends to be angry
表面上她还假真生气喔
Oh...yeah...she’s pretending
啊…伊…会学巴比补
First love is filled with emotions
初邵爱情酸甘甜，五种气味喃
I flush when she says she loves me
若丹一句我爱你，满面是红喷咏
Fuck! I’m looking at the characters!
哭天 ! 看字啦 !
Your owner's wife is older than you
人家你老关娘年如比你大
And she has 3 kids too
然后又已经有三个小孩
What matters is her husband is still alive
最重要的是她老公膛没死
What the hell are you thinking?
你到底在干嘛呀你 *
Have you seen breeding frogs?
你看过青蛙交配没有=
A couple of male frogs get on one female's back
一焦母青蛙背上贴著南三焦公青蛙
Those male frogs...
那丙三焦公青蛙
Do they fight one another?
有没有在那这互相吵架的=
No!
没有啊 !
Then why should we human beings...
那人干嘛去计较那一男一女
... insist on monogamy?
两男一女的事呢 =
Right on!
你属害 !
Aga! Come out!
阿嘉， 出来 !
Come out!
给我出来
Why don’t you come out?
入什么不敢滚出来=
You're too proud!
你在跨什么 !
Why did you treat me like that?
你每天装那个什么腑啊
Aga!
阿嘉!
You're so cocky!
你趾什感…
Why did you do this to me?
你为什么要期负我
I'm simply doing my job
我只不过在做我该做的事
What are you laughing at?
你笑什感啦…
Damn you!
你可恶啦你 !
I got you!
喔…被我发现了
Look at this
你看
This is my princess
过是我的鲁凯公主
She’s pretty, isn’t she?
长的很漂亮吧 =
Isn't she pretty?
真的很漂亮啦 !
If you see her, please tell her...
如果你有看到她的上时候，告诉她…
Why did you do this to me?
你为什么要期负我
rmagirl...
我一个女生
.. away from home
识家那不
I'm working here
在过里工作
And I work very hard
又那厂辛苦
Why did you do this to me?
你为什么要期负我
Evening. We're on the Sea of Japan
傍晚 ，已经进入了日本海
My head ached badly earlier today
白天我头痛欲裂
I hate this thick fog
可恨的湾需
It blocked my sight during the day
阻挡了我一整个白天的视乡
But the stars are beautiful
而现在的星光真美
Remember when you were in 7th grade...
记得你才是中学一年级小女生时
you challenged my lunar eclipse theory
就脸到以天狗食月的农村传说
...with the myth of Moon being eaten?
来挑战我月触的天文理葵吗”
I'll tell you another scientific truth
再说一件不怕你挑战的理请
Do you know the stars we see now...
你知道我们现在所看到的星光
...are lights reflected...
是自赤估光年鼻的星球上
...from billions of light-years away?
所发射过来的吧”
Wow! Billions of light-years away!
哇，炎估光年发射出来的光
And we haven't seen them until now
我们现在才看到
In billions of light-years...
泡估光年的台湾马和日本篇
...what will Taiwan and Japan become of?
又是什感样子呢
Mountains and seas will still be there
山还是山，海还是海
But the people will be gone
和邹不见了人
l want to take another glimpse at the sky
我想再多看汉眼星空
In this changeable world...
在过什么都善购的人世间壬
...l want to see what eternity is
我想看一下永是
I met a school of grey mullet heading to Taiwan for the winter
遇见了要往台湾避冬的篇负群
I trust my love to you to one of them
我把对你的相思寄放在其中的一焦
May your fisherman father catch it
希望你的省人父亲可以捕获
Tomoko, though it tastes bad...
友子，催管他的气味辛酸
... you have to try it anyway
你也一定要虹一口
You'll understand...
你会明白…
...that I didn’t mean to leave you
我不是抛辜你，我是拾不得你
I'm moaning on the deck at night...
我在和深人熟睡的甲板上反覆低喃
You really expect anything from us?
你真的期待我们各些破钢业”
But after 15 years...
可是我过了十五年
...[ fail after all
还不是一样失败
Though I’m not really that bad
可是我真的不差 !
A new day dawns, but who cares?
天亮了，, 但又有何关作
Sunlight only brings thick mist anyway
反正日光和煽是带来湾喜
I saw before dawn...
黎明前的一段习属
...the aged you from the future...
我见到了日后的你韶华已逝
...and the aged me from the future
日后的我朋秃眼垂
The morning mist covers my wrinkles on the forehead
晨雷如疆雪，履其了我额上的负纹
The sun scorches your black hair
师阳如烈焰，焚枯了你秀受的马黑
I've lost you completely
你我心中最后一点族热完全凋零
Please forgive the cowardly me
请原访我吉身扰用的身体
Those letters are very important
那些信件非常重要
You have to give them to that girl...
不管怎样
... whatever it takes
你一定要交到那个女孩手壬
Oh, Jeez!
糟糕…
Who did this?
谁弄的啊
You idiot! You'll be put into jail!
傻傻的你，各会判刑耶 !
I told you to return the mail but you opened it instead?
旱叫你退回日本了还偷拆别人邮包
Cape No.7, Hengchun
量春郡海角七号
Kojima Tomoko?
小息友子
I don’t remember this person
我怎厂不记得有各个人
We're about the same age if she’s still alive
吉如果还在，应该也大我没翅旗呀 !
It's 16 degrees Celsius here...
海上气温16度
... with a 12-knot wind above the 97-meter-deep sea
风速12节、水深97米
I've seen a couple of sea birds
已经看见了炮焦海马
We're landing tomorrow night
预计明天入夜前我们即将登陆
I left you all my photos taken in Taiwan
我把我在台湾的相筹都留给你
I gave them to your mother
就寄放在你母亲那儿
But I took one of them with me
但我偷了其中一张
It's you playing at the beach
是你在海亡玩水的那张
The sea in the photo is so calm...
照片里的海没风也没雨
...and your smiles fascinate me
照片里的你，笑得就像在天堂
Whoever your new lover will be...
不管你的未来将属於谁
...he can’t be good enough for you
谁都配不上你
I thought I packed all my beautiful memories
原本以为我能将美好回尽安善打包
Now I realize that alll can take away is emptiness
到头来务发现我能揣走的只有虚无
l really miss you!
我真的很想你 !
Wow! Rainbow!
啊，彩虹 !
May the rainbow bridge the two ends of ocean
但原吉彩虹的两端
...and bridge you and me
足以跨明海洋，过和结我和你
When sunshine returns
当阳光再次回到那…
To the rainy southern country
疆著雨的国境之南
lll try to finish
我会试著把…
The love story in the past
那一年的故事…再接下去褒完
When sunshine...
当阳光再次…
So many strings. I can’t do it right
过笋那友多人条 ，真的不好弹…
It's a love song!
各慢歌耶 !
It's easy. Only a few chords
很简哩的东西，又没汉个和粥
Come on!
拜旗 !
Let me tell you something Come earlier to practice tomorrow
不然， 你明天提早来练好不好
I never use these two strings
是说各两休都没用到
Can I cut them off?
不能把它草掉唉”
No, you can’t!
不行啦 ! 什么剪掉 !
Say it nicely. Why did you shout?
不行就不行，那友大蓝干嘛Y
Have you found that girl?
你有去找那信壬的女孩唉=
I tried, but didn’t find her
我找了…不过还汽找到…
I'll try harder
我会再找的
The lyrics...
歌词…
I know. I'll revise them
我知道，我会再修啦 !
So...l have to go
那…我先回去修润嘱 !
I need to turn off the lights
我，关烛
Il do it
我来，我来就好
All right, it’s up to you guys
好啦…你们自己看他行不行啦 !
Yeah, I think he can do it well
啊 ! 应该没什么问题吧
I think so too
应该可以啦 !
Damn!
堤!
You were so quick to answer
要回答得过厂快吗 * 不考虑就回答
I'm senile!
我老人家耶 !
You hurt my feelings
我心肝不是铁打的，我也会伤心耶 !
It's you who brought him here, not us
…人是你找来的，又不是我们找的
Yeah! We don’t even know him
对啊 ! 我们跟他又不款
Never mind me, Old Mao
茂伯 ! 我没关傈啦 !
Come on! I know what you want
别装了啦 ! 试鬼和还装客气
You're cocky only because you can play the bass guitar?
会弹具斯就那友慢张
Why can’t we have two bass guitarists?
将道就不能有两个弹有具斯的吗 =
Any instrument is all right for me
我不管，给我弹什三都好啦 !
l have to be on stage
我一定要上人台表演啦 !
Damn! They say I’m a gem!
干，我国需耶 !
Tomoko, I’ve landed safely
友子，我已经平安著陆
After the seven-day voyage...
七天的航行
...[ finally step on my homeland
我终於踩上我战丛葡破的土地
But I miss the sea already
可是我吨开始思念海洋
Why is the sea standing for...
二海洋为何入是站在
...the two extremes of hope and death?
希望和沽绝的两个极端
This is my last letter to you
过是我的最后一封信
I'll mail them later
待会我就会把信寄出去
This sea can’t tolerate love
过容不下爱情的海洋
At least it can tolerate lovesickness
至少膛容得下相思吧 !
Tomoko, you must receive my lovesickness
友子，我的相思你一定要收到
So that you'll forgive me a little bit
过样你才会原谅我一点点
I'll bury you in my heart forever
我想我会把你放在我心里一理子
Even when I'm getting married...
就算娶麦、生子
...or at some turning points of life...
在人生重要的转折烛上
...’m bound to think of you
一定会浮现…
The girl who ran away from home...
你提著笨重的行李逃家
... Standing alone in the crowd...
在遣返的人潮中，你孤单地站著
... wearing the white hat...
你戴著那项…
... which you'd worked so hard to buy
存了好久的钱才买来的白色对柚帆
You wanted me to recognize you in the crowd, didn’t you?
是为了让我能在人群中发现你吧 !
Il saw you...1 saw you...
我看见了…我看见了…
You were standing there silently
你安静不动地站著
It's an old address. Anyone knows?
蓄地址，海角七号…海角=
You're like the July sun
你像七月的烈日
I dare not glimpse at you any longer
让我不敢再多看你一眼
l saw you standing there silently
你站得如此安玫
You lit up my chilled heart
我刻意冰沪的心, 公又顿时燃起
l was sad, but had to hide my feelings
我伤心，又不敢让簿憾流露
I didn’t speak anything
我心里喃咕，员巴仓一普不咏
I know that my lovesickness...
我知道，思念过庸俗的字眼
...1S like the shadow under the sun...
将如阳光下的黑影
... chased by me and chasing me...
我逃他追…我追他逃…
...for the eternity
一理子
Why are you so sad?
为什么发愁呢=
Because of love? Of work?
感情* 工作=
Or is it because of us?
是我们害的唉=
I'm afraid it'll still be raining tomorrow
我是想过样下雨明天表演怎友办?
Miss Tomoko...
友子小姐…
Aren’t you expecting the rainbow?
交道你不期待彩虹唉=
Tomoko...
友子
l wrote my guiltiness in my last letter...
我把自己的愧次博成最丛一封信
...to show my apology to you
代替我去当面跟你届悔
That's how I can forgive myself
过样我才会原访自己一点点
Hey, you two!
喂，你们两焦马 !
No singing for you tomorrow on stage Can you live with that?
明天你们真的过样就甘愿了=
l was sleepless last night, thinking
我咱晚想了一整晚没睡
I've played yukin for more than 50 years
我弹月琴弹五十多年了
I'll be on stage for the first time tomorrow and I'll be shaking this?
明天第一次上人台竟然拿吉支在摇
Hey, you!
喂, 你啊!
You can sing very well
你唱歌也很好册啊 !
Don’t you want to sing on stage?
明天准道就不想哼两句
I think...
我觉得喔…
Shut up! No one asks you anything
你安静，我没问你 !
Hey, slam-dunker...
喂， 那个灌和著高手…
Red hair is not trendy now
红色不流行了啦 !
Aga is home revising the lyrics
阿嘉说他先在家里修改了歌局
He asked us to rehearse without him
他叫我们先自己业习
Today, 1 bought something for each of you at the airport
我今天在机塌买东西要途和给你们
Dada, this is Ancestors’ Eyes...
大大，过是祖填的眼睛
...to protect your health
保访你的身体健康成长
Thank you
谢谢
Malasun!
马拉桑 !
This is Bead of Butterfly Pupa...
过是蝶晴之珠
...to bring you fortune...
希望你的勤旁带给你
...for your diligence
很大很大的财富
Thanks. Fortune is all 1 need
谢谢…我需要财富…
Frog!
水蛙 !
This is Bead of Hands and Legs...
过是手脚之珠
...to improve your craftsmanship
让你的手艺更好
Rauma...
交马
This is Bead of Peacock...
过是孔雀之珠
...to guard your love for your wife
守灸你对你太太坚定的爱情
This is Bead of Tears
过是汇痕之珠
It's my lifelong aching for my wife
各个，对我妻子最不拾的思念
But ! bought it. Wear it anyway
戴著吧，都买了
You're aching because of love
有爱情，才会有思念呀 !
Thank you...
谢谢…
Old Mao!
茂伯呀 !
Duck’s grandpa is playing the timbrel now
骗尾他阿公现在只是销鼓手而已喔
Playing the timbrel is good as well
什么锥鼓手，丛鼓手又怎样*
Old Mao! This is Bead of Sunshine
茂介呀 ! 禹是日光之珠
It represents your nobility
象征你尊贵的地位 !
l have Mazu too. Won't they fight?
我过有刀祖耶，不会吵架唉”
No, they won't!
不会啦 !
We're all family. Why should we fight?
大家都是一家人“，人怎会吵架
Speaking of family...
讲到一家人
Actually l have something for you
其实，我有淮人备一个东西
We need unification...
就我们是一个乐团对不对
.. because we're all part of the band
要让人家看起来真的很有整体感
l had these custom-made earlier
所以之前我有去订作一个东西
And I'll give them to you right now
反正今天我觉得最通合
This is my own design
我特别订做了一件过个…
It's our uniform actually...
其实是我们的制服
...for us to wear on stage
表演的时候可以穿的
Uniform?
制服?
Malasun
马拉桑
Thousands years of history with new sensation
干年传统，全新感受
The uniform for family
一家人的制服
Sorry to bother you
不好意思，借坐一下
Make yourselves at home. I'll be in my room
你们在过里忙，我先去休息
The breeze informs of Spring’s coming
微风告知春天来访
The fragrance of blooming flowers...
纷稚种放的花洒香气壬
...reminds me of you far away
令人想起鼻方的你
You're like a blooming flower in the sunshine of Spring
如春日阳光守访下和绽放的花洒
The light of hope will lead us well into the future
未来 希望之光也会照耀我们吧
We're stepping on the roads we chose
我们各自踏上各自抉择的道路
Now I know...
我终於知道为什么大家都说
...why people said 1 sang too hard
我以前唱歌太用力
Aga, l...
阿嘉，我…
Are you all here? It’s your turn
你们人到元了吗 * 损你们彩排了
All right?
可以了唉Y
Atari, all right?
孝介，可以了吗?
-OK! -Yeah, l see
从 ! -是的,我知道了
Please
麻烦你了
Do me a favor
跟罗商量一下好不好
I'll make a DVD
等一下我去烧一张光碟
Project our logo on that big screen
把我们的商标打在那个大痊幕上面
It's the best way of promotion
人各记多，效果一定…
Don’t ask too much!
你不要太过分…
You've got the T-shirts
已经给你吉样子了
Thanks a lot!
辛苦了 !
Let's have a rest in the hotel
我们先到饭店壬面休息一下
Tomoko, can you ask them to prepare the meal?
友子，可以先请府房先淮人备终点吗?
That policeman is the band’s guitarist
那警察是暖声乐围的吉他手 !
Policeman?
名突一 树冰
You're very popular in Taiwan
没想到你在台湾各友受欢迎
Miss Tomoko...
友子小姐
Rainbow!
彩虹 !
Can I have a cigarette?
可以给我一根粳吗=
Don’t tell me you don’t speak Japanese
别跟我说你英不懂日文
After today...
今天过和后
...you don’t have to see us anymore
你就不必看到我们吉些计屎的人了
I'm in love with Aga
我爱上阿嘉了 !
But this is different
只是过次最奇怪
I don’t know if it’s love or not
不知道到底算不算 =
You Japanese don’t know what love is
日本人哪懂爱情=
Have you been hurt by any Japanese?
你被日本人伤明心唉=
Why are you so prejudiced?
人怎且对我们那友偏见”
Is it Dada’s father?
是大大的父亲唉?
He must've hurt you really bad
你一定被男人伤得很重!
My heart died long ago
早就心死了 !
I'm looking for a girl in Hengchun whose heart died too
我也在寻找一位心死的恒春女陀
She’s probably 80 years old now
不过他现在大概也八十诚了吧 !
Her name is also Tomoko
他也和我一样叫友子 !
Il saw a package at Aga’s place
我在阿嘉那亡看到一个邮包
A Japanese package with an unknown address
一个找不到地址的日本邮包
Or more aptly put...
更正确的府
...there are seven love letters in it
应该是七封情书
When the Japanese old man died...
日本老先生死了之后
...his daughter found them in his closet
他女儿和在他柜子里找到
She mailed them on his behalf
替他寄过来的 !
Unfortunately, no one remembers an old address 60 years ago
可惜60年前的蓄地址已经没人记得
l read those love letters
我…偷看过那些情书
Never seen anything more beautiful
那是我所网过最真最美的思念
It'd comfort the lovesick old lady
一定可以医治一位心死的老人 !
What's the matter with you?
你怎磋了=
Send the package to this address
把邮包泛到过个地址
That Tomoko lives here
那个也叫友子的女孩住在过里 !
How do you know that?
…你怎友知道?
She’s my grandmother
她是我祖母 !
Then...I'll give the package to you
那…我把邮包拿给你啊 !
I did something bad to her
我对她做了很不好的事
She doesn’t want to see me anymore
她已经不理我了 !
Go ahead!
快去吧 !
Gol
快去啊 !
I found the owner of the package
找到邮包的主人了 !
Can you go now?
你可以现在去唉”
That urgent?
有那厂急吗=
Aga...
阿嘉
When the concert is over...
今天晚上表演结束
...P Il. go back to Japan...
我就要和日本唱片公司的人
...with the Japanese staff
一起回日本
They offered me a job in Japan
他们洲请我到日本唱片公司当公天
And you accepted?
你答认了=
Don’t forget to tell me...
记得告诉我
... what that Tomoko looks like
那个也叫友子的女孩的长相喔 !
This is Bead of Warrior...
过是勇士之珠
...to guard your honor and bravery
他会保谨你的妆内和勇到
I'll pretend that you forget me...
我会假装你忘了我
...that you send your love to me away...
假装你将你我的过往
... like a migrating bird
像候篇一般从记居中迁徙
...and that you throw the past away
假装你已走过蹇冬迎接春天
I'll pretend...
我会假装…
...until believe everything I imagine
一直到自以为一切都是真的 !
...l' ll wish you all the happiness
祝你一生永束幸福 !
Anybody home?
有人在唉Y
Hey! What did you say to Aga?
你到底跟阿嘉说什么啊
Those near the sea water...
靠海这的朋友
Please come closer!
麻烦你们站进来一点
The tide is ebbing
现在在退潮
Thank you!
谢谢 !
Be careful! Come closer!
小心 ! 靠进来一点
What were you thinking?
你有没有搞错啊
You asked him to send a mail?
到底什感时候了“，你还叫人了他去途信?
What's wrong with you?
你到底有没有进入状况啊
Mr. Manager...
经理
...wanna contact Mr. Representative?
要不要跟代表会主席连和络一下=
He may be in the crowd
他可能在人群里面 !
What good will it do?
找他有个屁用啊Y
Do something! Do you hear me?
你起快给我想办法，册到洛有=
Miss Tomoko...
友子小姐
Is there anyone who can sing?
他们有谁可以唱的唉=
I can sing very well!
我很能唱 !
Ask him if you don’t believe me
不信和的话，你可以问他
Ask him
软问他啊 !
Aga’s here!
啊，阿嘉回来了 !
What took you so long?
你怎厂去那友久?
Didn't they hate each other?
他们两个不是仇人唉?
Stay...
留下来…
...or Ill go with you
或者我跟浆走 !
Don’t be nervous! Relax!
不要桶张，放轻县
Who’s nervous? Idiot!
谁紧张 * 神经病 !
l wanna collect the warmth of Summer
想萤集夏天的热
Wanna cross the river named Happiness
穿越叫幸福的河
Wanna be a snake swallowing elephant
想做吞大象的蛇
It sounds stupid, but why not?
不自量力府真的，有何不可
When the sky is empty and the earth is dry
当天是空的，地是乾的
I'm pouring passion for you
我要为你倒进狂热
l want the whole world to know you're mine
让全世界知道录是我的
The weather's gone mad and the sea is boiling
天和气瘤了，海水滚了
That's why I want to seize the day
所以我要扰乐不作
Stop wasting time
不要浪费每一刻，快乐
Be a skywalker...
当芝的天行者
An angel like you
像你各样的天使
Should have wings and name
该有翅膀和名字
Should have fatal beauty
该美看中带著刺
Should belong to me for once
该很认真的属於我一次
When the sky is empty and the earth is dry
当天是空的，地是乾的
I'm pouring passion for you
我要为你倒进狂热
l want the whole world to know you're mine
让全世界知道录是我的
The weather's gone mad and the sea is boiling
天和气瘤了，海水滚了
That's why I want to seize the day -Grandpa!
所以我要无乐不作 -阿公…
Stop wasting time
不要浪费每一刻，快乐
Be a skywalker...
当芝的天行者
When the sky is empty and the earth is dry
当天是空的，地是乾的
I'm pouring passion for you
我要为你倒进狂热
l want the whole world to know that you're mine
让全世界知道录是我的
The end of the world scares me not
世界末日就仇管来吧
I'll keep on enjoying myself
我会楼炉扰乐不作
‘Cause loving you makes me happy
不会浪费爱你的，快乐
Be a skywalker...
当芝的天行者
Be happy, oh...
要快乐，喔一
Relax! What are you afraid of?
不要紧张嘛 ! 怕什感
Here. Take this
过支给你控
If Sea can talk and if Wind falls in love with Sands
如果海会说话，如果风爱上砂
If my longing’s lost in vacancy
如果有些想念遗忘在某个长假
I'll listen to the waves Let the wind blow my hair
我会险匡浪花，让风吹过藉爱
My love for you grows with time
任记尽里的爱情在时间潮汐里喧唑
Summer's here when Spring’s away
非得等春天和球了，夏天才近了
I finally realize on retrospect
我是在回首时和终於懂得
When sunshine returns
当阳光再砍回到那
To the rainy southern country
疆著雨的国境之南
lll try to finish
我会试著把…
The love story
那一年的故事
In the past
再接下去褒完
When sunshine leaves
当阳光再次购并那
The too sunny southern country
太晴朗的国境之南
Will you give me back
你会不会把…
All the love you took away
您曾带走的爱
Before you said goodbye
在告别前用微笑全刀膛
Sea is blue. Stars shine bright
海很艺，星光烧烟
My arms are empty without you
我们空著我的尼蕉
Sky is endless at my lonely nights
天很宽，在我独自唱歌的夜晚
Please forgive my hesitancy
请原夕我的爱
To confess that I love you
诉说的太楼慢
This is Bead of Peacock...
过是孔雀之珠
...to guard your everlasting love
她守汶著你坚真不移的爱情 !
When sunshine returns
当阳光再砍回到那
To the rainy southern country
疆著雨的国境之南
lll try to finish
我会试著把…
The love story
那一年的故事
In the past
再接下去褒完
The rainbow... Thank you very much
彩虹的事，谢谢你 !
Don’t mention it
汽事…
Will you give me back
你会不会把…
All the love you took away
您曾带走的爱
Before you said goodbye
在告别前用微笑全刀膛
It's all right. Let them sing one more
没关傈的，就让他们再唱一首吧 !
No, they only have two songs
不行呵，他们只淮人备两首歌
Come here!
过来啦 !
Old Mao!
成伯 !
A boy sees a wild rose
男孩看见野表现
Ah! I know that song too
啊，和吉首歌我也会唱
It blooms so early in the morning
清早盛开真侠美
He rushes to see it clearly
急忙跑去近前看
The rose makes him happy
说看越忱区心
Rose, rose, the red rose
玫瑰玫瑰红表瑰
The rose in the wilderness
荒地上的玫瑰
Miss Tomoko...
友子小姐
These are the letters my father wrote
我是过信件中老师的女儿
l accidentally found them in my father's bedroom closet
吉木盒是在父亲房间衣村里发现的
My father died in January this year
我的父亲已经在今年一月病逝了
l read every one of the letters
我仔细的看过里面的每一封信
How the beautiful secrets...
很难想像木盒里的秘密…
...hidden in them broke my heart
是如此的美焉而辛酸
I mailed these letters he wrote...
现在我就代替我的父亲
... which he was supposed to send...
把吉些六十年前的信
...60 years ago
全部寄过去给你
Sorry for keeping you waiting for so long
很抱舟，让你久等了